Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
एडमिन सहायता देखें kissasia.cam या kisskh.org पर
[The Guardians]
[अभिभावक]
[Episode 25]
[एपिसोड 25]
In mid-1941,
1941 के मध्य में,
the Japanese army was vigorously
जापानी सेना जोरदार तरीके से
preparing for the Pacification Operation,
शांति अभियान की तैयारी ,
trying to boost economic plunder of the occupied areas
कब्जे वाले क्षेत्रों की आर्थिक लूट को बढ़ावा देने की कोशिश
and destroy the Chinese army's
और चीनी सेना को नष्ट कर दें
anti-Japanese armed forces behind enemy lines.
दुश्मन की रेखाओं के पीछे जापानी विरोधी सशस्त्र बलों की तैनाती ।
[May 1941]
[मई 1941]
[Pacification Committee Preparatory Meeting]
[शांति समिति की तैयारी बैठक]
Let us toast to the smooth conclusion
आइये हम सुखद निष्कर्ष के लिए टोस्ट करें
of the Pacification Committee's
शांति समिति के
preparatory meeting.
तैयारी बैठक.
Cheers.
प्रोत्साहित करना।
Major General.
महा सेनापति।
[New Asia Hotel]
[न्यू एशिया होटल]
The Pacification Committee's secret radio code
शांति समिति का गुप्त रेडियो कोड
will be settled today.
आज निपटारा हो जाएगा।
With our current relationship,
हमारे वर्तमान रिश्ते के साथ,
is it appropriate to talk about this?
क्या इस बारे में बात करना उचित है?
We have different stances.
हमारे रुख अलग-अलग हैं।
So all this time,
तो इस पूरे समय,
no matter how we secretly competed,
चाहे हम गुप्त रूप से कितनी भी प्रतिस्पर्धा करें,
I had nothing to say.
मेरे पास कहने को कुछ नहीं था.
But you don't have to make a desperate move for help, right?
लेकिन आपको मदद के लिए कोई हताश कदम उठाने की जरूरत नहीं है , है ना?
You know very well
आप बहुत अच्छी तरह जानते हैं
what kind of person Liang Jingyuan is.
लिआंग जिंगयुआन किस तरह का व्यक्ति है?
Working with him is like asking a tiger for its skin.
उनके साथ काम करना बाघ से उसकी खाल मांगने जैसा है।
My niece.
मेरी भतीजी.
Yes, yes.
हां हां।
Let's head over there.
चलो वहाँ चलें.
Liang Jingyuan really knows how to climb up.
लिआंग जिंगयुआन वास्तव में जानता है कि कैसे ऊपर चढ़ना है।
I never thought the Pacification Committee
मैंने कभी नहीं सोचा था कि शांति समिति
would actually make him a committee member.
वास्तव में वह समिति का सदस्य बन जाएगा।
If you had a wife willing to use her family money
अगर आपकी पत्नी अपने परिवार के पैसे का इस्तेमाल करने को तैयार हो
to smooth things over for you,
आपके लिए चीज़ें सुचारू करने के लिए,
you'd climb faster than he does.
आप उससे अधिक तेजी से चढ़ेंगे।
Hello, Director Lee.
नमस्ते, निदेशक ली।
Director Lee.
निर्देशक ली.
Mr. Lin and Mr. Tang are here too.
श्री लिन और श्री तांग भी यहां हैं।
Mr. Lee.
श्री ली।
Major General Sasaki has arrived.
मेजर जनरल सासाकी आ गए हैं।
This is Lieutenant General Yasui from the East Asia Development Board.
मैं पूर्वी एशिया विकास बोर्ड से लेफ्टिनेंट जनरल यासुई हूं।
He is also one of the advisers to the Pacification Committee.
वह शांति समिति के सलाहकारों में से एक भी हैं ।
Mr. Yasui.
श्री यासुई।
It's an honor to meet you.
आपसे मिलना सम्मान की बात है।
Mr. Lee.
श्री ली।
I've heard much about you.
मैंने आपके बारे में बहुत कुछ सुना है।
Grand Duke and I are old friends.
ग्रैंड ड्यूक और मैं पुराने दोस्त हैं।
Back when he was serving as ambassador to the UK,
जब वे ब्रिटेन में राजदूत के रूप में कार्यरत थे,
he often mentioned you to me.
वह अक्सर मुझसे तुम्हारा ज़िक्र करता था।
I didn't expect to meet you here.
मुझे आपसे यहां मिलने की उम्मीद नहीं थी।
May we speak privately?
क्या हम अकेले में बात कर सकते हैं?
I'd like to have a private chat with Mr. Lee.
मैं श्री ली के साथ निजी बातचीत करना चाहूंगा ।
Please, go ahead.
कृपया आगे जाएं।
Secretary Gu.
सचिव गु.
Since Mr. Yasui has an interpreter with him,
चूँकि श्री यासुई के साथ एक दुभाषिया है,
you don't need to accompany me.
तुम्हें मेरे साथ आने की जरूरत नहीं है.
Alright, Director Lee.
ठीक है, निदेशक ली.
Please come in.
कृपया अंदर आएं।
I will definitely think of something for you.
मैं आपके लिए अवश्य कुछ सोचूंगा ।
Let's talk.
चलो बात करते हैं।
Cheers.
प्रोत्साहित करना।
Mr. Liang, what's the matter
श्रीमान लियांग, क्या बात है?
calling me out?
मुझे बुला रहे हो?
I just saw it all.
मैंने अभी-अभी यह सब देखा है।
They didn't let you in.
उन्होंने तुम्हें अन्दर नहीं आने दिया.
What does that tell you?
उसकी ओर से तुमसे क्या कहा जाता है?
He's already treating you differently.
वह पहले से ही आपके साथ अलग व्यवहार कर रहा है।
I'm used to it.
मैं इसके लिए इस्तेमाल कर रहा हूँ।
I'm just an assistant.
मैं तो सिर्फ एक सहायक हूं.
It's kind of strange, though.
हालाँकि, यह थोड़ा अजीब है।
Lieutenant General Yasui
लेफ्टिनेंट जनरल यासुई
suddenly came here.
अचानक यहाँ आ गया.
On the surface, Mr. Yasui
सतह पर, श्री यासुई
is an adviser to the Pacification Committee.
शांति समिति के सलाहकार हैं ।
But in reality, he's here to investigate
लेकिन वास्तव में, वह यहाँ जांच करने के लिए है
those in the New Government's intelligence agencies
नई सरकार की खुफिया एजेंसियों में शामिल लोग
who secretly have ties to the British and American forces.
जिनके गुप्त रूप से ब्रिटिश और अमेरिकी सेनाओं से संबंध हैं ।
Joseph Lee is British, after all.
आखिरकार, जोसेफ ली ब्रिटिश हैं।
Mr. Liang,
श्री लियांग,
are you planning to move against Mr. Lee?
are you planning to move against Mr. Lee?
But as far as I know,
But as far as I know,
Mr. Yasui and Grand Duke Tonoji
Mr. Yasui and Grand Duke Tonoji
have been old friends of many years.
have been old friends of many years.
Would he not show Grand Duke some respect?
Would he not show Grand Duke some respect?
Stop saying Mr. Liang.
Stop saying Mr. Liang.
I've already told you we are friends.
I've already told you we are friends.
Let me put it this way.
Let me put it this way.
Grand Duke Tonoji and Mr. Yasui
Grand Duke Tonoji and Mr. Yasui
do have a good relationship.
do have a good relationship.
But in the struggle between
But in the struggle between
the Tonoji family and the Tōjō faction,
the Tonoji family and the Tōjō faction,
he has always remained neutral.
he has always remained neutral.
Moreover, Grand Duke
Moreover, Grand Duke
was the ambassador to the UK for many years.
was the ambassador to the UK for many years.
All his family assets are in London.
All his family assets are in London.
If war breaks out with Britain and America,
If war breaks out with Britain and America,
the first to suffer will be him.
the first to suffer will be him.
Besides, he's been bedridden for over a year.
Besides, he's been bedridden for over a year.
We don't know whether he'll wake up.
We don't know whether he'll wake up.
So for Joseph Lee,
So for Joseph Lee,
is the Tonoji family
is the Tonoji family
a life-saving talisman or a death warrant?
a life-saving talisman or a death warrant?
What do you think?
आप क्या सोचते हैं?
Please, Liang, enlighten me.
Please, Liang, enlighten me.
This is a letter of accusation.
This is a letter of accusation.
I've already written the contents for you
I've already written the contents for you
in your identity and tone,
in your identity and tone,
accusing the British Joseph Lee of colluding with Britain and America.
accusing the British Joseph Lee of colluding with Britain and America.
It only needs your signature.
It only needs your signature.
But if I sign this letter of accusation,
But if I sign this letter of accusation,
then Mr. Lee will be doomed.
then Mr. Lee will be doomed.
Let me ask you.
Let me ask you.
You're always thinking of him.
You're always thinking of him.
But have you ever thought
But have you ever thought
whether he's ever thought of you?
whether he's ever thought of you?
If Joseph Lee always remains
If Joseph Lee always remains
the director of the Cryptography Institute,
the director of the Cryptography Institute,
he'll always keep you under him.
he'll always keep you under him.
Are you willing?
Are you willing?
As long as you sign this letter of accusation,
As long as you sign this letter of accusation,
Major General Sasaki will sign
Major General Sasaki will sign
your appointment letter.
your appointment letter.
Then you will be the Code Officer
Then you will be the Code Officer
for the Pacification Committee.
for the Pacification Committee.
Sasaki will be your big tree to rely on.
Sasaki will be your big tree to rely on.
Let alone one set of codes,
Let alone one set of codes,
all your talents
all your talents
[1941, Pacification Committee]
[1941, Pacification Committee]
will be seen by others.
will be seen by others.
[Letter of Appointment]
[Letter of Appointment]
Did Yasui say anything to you?
Did Yasui say anything to you?
What did Liang Jingyuan say to you?
What did Liang Jingyuan say to you?
The Pacification Committee has already adopted
The Pacification Committee has already adopted
the code he designed.
the code he designed.
And the one you designed
And the one you designed
was rejected by Nanjing. Did you know?
was rejected by Nanjing. Did you know?
He said you went behind my back
He said you went behind my back
and gave the Japanese
and gave the Japanese
a highly sophisticated code.
a highly sophisticated code.
It seems your new assistant
It seems your new assistant
is quite capable.
is quite capable.
But I still have to remind you.
But I still have to remind you.
Even if the Pacification Committee uses your code,
Even if the Pacification Committee uses your code,
we will not stop here.
we will not stop here.
I will also remind you one last time.
I will also remind you one last time.
Don't trust Liang Jingyuan too much.
Don't trust Liang Jingyuan too much.
I understand.
मैं समझता हूँ।
Now, looking at
Now, looking at
the recovery of the leg nerves,
the recovery of the leg nerves,
on a scale of one to ten,
on a scale of one to ten,
rate the intensity of the sensation you feel.
rate the intensity of the sensation you feel.
One means no sensation at all.
One means no sensation at all.
Ten means very strong sensation.
Ten means very strong sensation.
Then let's begin.
Then let's begin.
How intense is it?
How intense is it?
Two or three.
Two or three.
I understand.
मैं समझता हूँ।
Then how about here?
Then how about here?
How is it?
कैसा है?
Five, I think.
Five, I think.
Doctor.
Doctor.
The corridor is less than 100 meters long,
The corridor is less than 100 meters long,
yet she needs ten minutes to walk it with a walker.
yet she needs ten minutes to walk it with a walker.
It's been such a long time.
It's been such a long time.
Why hasn't she recovered yet?
वह अभी तक ठीक क्यों नहीं हुई?
Although Mrs. Lee's spinal injury
हालाँकि श्रीमती ली की रीढ़ की हड्डी में चोट
has completely healed,
पूरी तरह से ठीक हो गया है,
spinal nerves recovery
रीढ़ की हड्डी की नसों की रिकवरी
is slower than expected.
अपेक्षा से धीमी है।
So,
इसलिए,
with her current nerve sensation,
उसकी वर्तमान तंत्रिका संवेदना के साथ,
being able to get out of bed
बिस्तर से बाहर निकलने में सक्षम होना
is already a miracle.
यह पहले से ही एक चमत्कार है।
She still needs to continue using nerve-nourishing medication
उसे अभी भी तंत्रिका-पोषण करने वाली दवा का उपयोग जारी रखने की आवश्यकता है
and increase rehabilitation training.
और पुनर्वास प्रशिक्षण में वृद्धि की जाएगी।
Take it slowly.
धीरे से।
Well then, I'll take my leave.
तो फिर मैं विदा लेता हूं।
I'll walk them out.
मैं उन्हें बाहर ले जाऊंगा.
That really hurt.
इससे सचमुच दुख हुआ।
Is who lives on the top floor really so important
क्या ऊपरी मंजिल पर रहने वाला व्यक्ति सचमुच इतना महत्वपूर्ण है?
that it's worth such a big risk?
क्या यह इतना बड़ा जोखिम उठाने लायक है?
Don't worry about me.
मेरी चिंता मत करो.
Once we find out the result,
एक बार जब हमें परिणाम पता चल जाता है,
I have ways to get out of it.
मेरे पास इससे बाहर निकलने के रास्ते हैं।
How about on your side? Is it going smoothly?
आपकी तरफ से क्या हाल है? क्या सब कुछ ठीक चल रहा है?
The code plan given to me by the Organization
संगठन द्वारा मुझे दी गई कोड योजना
has already been submitted to Nanjing.
नानजिंग को पहले ही प्रस्तुत किया जा चुका है।
In a few days,
कुछ ही दिनों में,
the Pacification Committee
शांति समिति
will officially use our code.
आधिकारिक तौर पर हमारे कोड का उपयोग करेंगे।
But I still don't feel entirely reassured.
लेकिन मैं अभी भी पूरी तरह आश्वस्त महसूस नहीं कर रहा हूं।
It's always good to be cautious.
सतर्क रहना हमेशा अच्छा होता है।
But remember,
लेकिन याद रखें,
don't put too much pressure on yourself.
अपने ऊपर बहुत अधिक दबाव न डालें.
Much of our territory behind enemy lines
हमारा अधिकांश क्षेत्र शत्रु की सीमाओं के पीछे है
and the Kuomintang's Loyal Salvation Army
और कुओमिन्तांग की वफादार मुक्ति सेना
have all been included
सभी को शामिल किया गया है
in the primary target area of this operation.
इस ऑपरेशन के प्राथमिक लक्ष्य क्षेत्र में ।
Only by gaining control
केवल नियंत्रण प्राप्त करके
of the secret radio code of the Pacification Committee
शांति समिति के गुप्त रेडियो कोड का
can we possibly learn about
क्या हम संभवतः इसके बारे में जान सकते हैं
the puppet army's operational movements.
कठपुतली सेना की परिचालन गतिविधियाँ।
From what I know of Gu Yangshan,
गु यांगशान के बारे में मैं जो जानता हूँ, उसके अनुसार,
he will definitely not give up.
वह निश्चित रूप से हार नहीं मानेगा।
Since the Wannan Incident,
वानन घटना के बाद से,
relations between the KMT and CCP have been deadlocked.
केएमटी और सीसीपी के बीच संबंधों में गतिरोध पैदा हो गया है।
For the past half year, you've been fighting alone,
पिछले आधे साल से आप अकेले ही लड़ रहे हैं,
openly against Liang Jingyuan,
लियांग जिंगयुआन के ख़िलाफ़ खुले तौर पर,
and secretly against Gu Yangshan.
और गुप्त रूप से गु यांगशान के खिलाफ।
You've suffered
आपने कष्ट सहे हैं
but also gathered valuable experience.
बल्कि बहुमूल्य अनुभव भी प्राप्त किया।
These two people are both very calculating.
ये दोनों लोग बहुत गणनाशील हैं।
Their alliance can't be simple.
उनका गठबंधन सरल नहीं हो सकता।
So I suspect
इसलिए मुझे संदेह है
the two of them
वो दो
will soon make their next move.
वे जल्द ही अपना अगला कदम उठाएंगे।
We can't sit still and wait.
हम चुपचाप बैठकर इंतजार नहीं कर सकते।
We must strike first,
हमें पहले हमला करना होगा,
and kick Gu Yangshan out of the game.
और गु यांगशान को खेल से बाहर कर दिया।
When can the code expert sent by the Organization
संगठन द्वारा भेजा गया कोड विशेषज्ञ कब
to support me come?
मेरा समर्थन करने के लिए आओ?
The background checks at the institute
संस्थान में पृष्ठभूमि की जाँच
are now personally handled by Sasaki.
अब सासाकी द्वारा व्यक्तिगत रूप से नियंत्रित किया जाता है।
The scrutiny is extremely strict.
जांच अत्यंत सख्त है।
We have been preparing for months.
हम महीनों से तैयारी कर रहे हैं।
The problem of faking the expert's identity
विशेषज्ञ की पहचान को फर्जी बनाने की समस्या
was only just solved in recent days.
हाल ही में इसका समाधान किया गया है।
Once you return, find a chance to request
एक बार जब आप वापस आ जाएं, तो अनुरोध करने का अवसर ढूंढें
that you need a new secretarial officer.
कि आपको एक नये सचिवीय अधिकारी की आवश्यकता है।
He will find a way to be transferred to your side.
वह आपके पक्ष में स्थानांतरित होने का रास्ता खोज लेगा ।
It's time to say goodbye.
यह अलविदा कहने का समय है।
[Shanghai Army No. 2 Hospital]
[शंघाई आर्मी नंबर 2 अस्पताल]
Slow down.
गति कम करो।
Careful, careful.
सावधान, सावधान.
Tell Xiao
जिओ को बताओ
the code replacement work for the Pacification Committee's
शांति समिति के लिए कोड प्रतिस्थापन कार्य
secret radio
गुप्त रेडियो
has been successfully completed by Ding Yi.
डिंग यी द्वारा सफलतापूर्वक पूरा कर लिया गया है ।
The expert we arranged for him
हमने उसके लिए जिस विशेषज्ञ की व्यवस्था की थी
can be ready to enter the institute at any time.
किसी भी समय संस्थान में प्रवेश के लिए तैयार हो सकते हैं ।
Alright.
ठीक है।
But what about your side?
लेकिन आपके पक्ष का क्या?
You're alone.
तुम अकेले में हो।
If the data is correct,
यदि डेटा सही है,
this Dr. Edward
यह डॉ. एडवर्ड
is the top cardiovascular surgeon today.
आज शीर्ष हृदय शल्य चिकित्सक हैं।
For the patient on the top floor to have the influence
ऊपरी मंजिल पर मौजूद मरीज पर प्रभाव डालने के लिए
to bring him here
उसे यहाँ लाने के लिए
shows he must be an important figure in the Japanese army.
इससे पता चलता है कि वह जापानी सेना में एक महत्वपूर्ण व्यक्ति होगा ।
I suspect it's Grand Duke Tonoji.
मुझे संदेह है कि यह ग्रैंड ड्यूक टोनोजी है।
But he's not the only person in the Japanese army
लेकिन वह जापानी सेना में अकेले व्यक्ति नहीं हैं
who has cardiovascular disease.
जिसे हृदय रोग है।
Why suspect only him?
केवल उसी पर संदेह क्यों?
Dr. Edward is British.
डॉ. एडवर्ड ब्रिटिश हैं।
Given the tense relations among Japan, the UK, and the US,
जापान, ब्रिटेन और अमेरिका के बीच तनावपूर्ण संबंधों को देखते हुए ,
apart from Grand Duke Tonoji,
ग्रैंड ड्यूक टोनोजी के अलावा,
who served in Britain for years
जिन्होंने वर्षों तक ब्रिटेन में सेवा की
and embraced Westernization,
और पश्चिमीकरण को अपनाया,
who else would dare to hire a British doctor
और कौन ब्रिटिश डॉक्टर को नौकरी पर रखने की हिम्मत करेगा
at such a critical time?
ऐसे नाजुक समय में?
But,
लेकिन,
according to the intelligence
खुफिया जानकारी के अनुसार
we received some time ago,
हमें कुछ समय पहले प्राप्त हुआ,
Grand Duke is still recuperating in Japan.
ग्रैंड ड्यूक अभी भी जापान में स्वास्थ्य लाभ कर रहे हैं।
Last time Ding Yi mentioned
पिछली बार डिंग यी ने उल्लेख किया था
that the Cryptography Institute had received
जो क्रिप्टोग्राफी संस्थान को प्राप्त हुआ था
a coded message from a private radio.
एक निजी रेडियो से कोडित संदेश।
Do you remember?
तुम्हे याद है?
I remember.
मुझे याद है।
Ding Yi told us the frequency of that radio
डिंग यी ने हमें उस रेडियो की आवृत्ति बताई
and the time of transmission.
और संचरण का समय.
After verification by higher-ups,
उच्च अधिकारियों द्वारा सत्यापन के बाद,
it turns out that it was Sasaki's private radio.
पता चला कि यह सासाकी का निजी रेडियो था।
But what does that have to do
लेकिन इसका क्या लेना-देना है?
with who's living upstairs?
ऊपर कौन रहता है?
The Sasaki family is a representative
सासाकी परिवार एक प्रतिनिधि है
of the Imperial Way faction in the military,
सेना में इंपीरियल वे गुट के ,
and an archenemy of the Tonoji family.
और टोनोजी परिवार का कट्टर दुश्मन।
Once our comrades in the rear finish decrypting,
एक बार जब हमारे पीछे के साथी डिक्रिप्ट करना समाप्त कर लेते हैं,
I believe the coded message from that radio
मुझे विश्वास है कि उस रेडियो से प्राप्त कोडित संदेश
will tell us
हमें बताएँगे
who the patient on the top floor
ऊपरी मंजिल पर मरीज कौन है
really is.
वास्तव में है.
Even if I have to get some gas now,
भले ही मुझे अभी कुछ गैस लेनी पड़े,
I still have to sign off, right?
मुझे अभी भी हस्ताक्षर करना है, है ना?
Then what am I still the Director of General Affairs?
तो फिर मैं अभी भी सामान्य मामलों का निदेशक हूं?
Why don't you let Xian Biyun take the job?
आप जियान बियुन को यह काम क्यों नहीं करने देते?
Signature.
हस्ताक्षर।
Signature from a blind man?
एक अंधे आदमी के हस्ताक्षर?
Can he even see?
क्या वह देख भी सकता है?
Liang.
लिआंग.
The Pacification Committee has been established.
शांति समिति की स्थापना की गई है।
When are we moving there?
हम वहां कब जा रहे हैं?
Stop reading.
पढ़ना बंद करो.
Don't you know English-language newspapers are contraband?
क्या आप नहीं जानते कि अंग्रेजी भाषा के समाचार पत्र प्रतिबंधित हैं?
Others might not know, but you should.
हो सकता है कि अन्य लोग न जानते हों, लेकिन आपको पता होना चाहिए।
The title of Pacification Committee member
शांति समिति के सदस्य का पद
is just an empty name.
यह तो बस एक खाली नाम है।
Am I really looking at the newspaper?
क्या मैं सचमुच अखबार देख रहा हूं?
I'm looking at my future.
मैं अपना भविष्य देख रहा हूं।
Nonsense.
बकवास।
Someone's occupied our place.
किसी ने हमारी जगह पर कब्ज़ा कर लिया है.
The living room's so small, it's like a piece of tofu.
लिविंग रूम इतना छोटा है कि वह टोफू के टुकड़े जैसा है।
You just had to be an official.
आपको तो बस एक अधिकारी बनना था।
And now look at where you've ended up.
और अब देखो कि तुम कहां पहुंच गये हो।
After all the effort we've spent,
हमारे द्वारा किये गए सभी प्रयासों के बाद,
you've even hurt your leg, but what for?
आपने तो अपना पैर भी चोटिल कर लिया, लेकिन किसलिए?
Alright.
ठीक है।
Don't touch me.
छूना नहीं मुझे।
Stop crying.
रोना बंद करो.
Do you think I just want to be an official?
क्या आपको लगता है कि मैं सिर्फ एक अधिकारी बनना चाहता हूं?
I'm trying to create
मैं बनाने की कोशिश कर रहा हूँ
a sense of security for both of us.
हम दोनों के लिए सुरक्षा की भावना.
You know perfectly well what the situation is now.
आप अच्छी तरह जानते हैं कि अब स्थिति क्या है।
The both of us
हम दोनों
are trying to survive here.
यहाँ जीवित रहने की कोशिश कर रहे हैं।
Everyone
सब लोग
goes through extremely difficult times.
अत्यंत कठिन समय से गुजर रहा है।
Once you get through it, things will be fine.
एक बार आप इससे पार पा लेंगे तो सब ठीक हो जाएगा।
Was there something you wanted from me?
क्या तुम मुझसे कुछ चाहते थे?
The Special Agent Headquarters just called,
विशेष एजेंट मुख्यालय ने अभी फोन किया,
saying they're assigning a new secretary to Joseph Lee.
उन्होंने कहा कि वे जोसेफ ली को नया सचिव नियुक्त कर रहे हैं।
Did you know?
क्या आप जानते हैं?
Is your information accurate?
क्या आपकी जानकारी सही है?
They just called.
उन्होंने अभी फोन किया।
That's great.
यह बहुत अच्छा है।
Don't say it.
ऐसा मत कहो.
No one should talk about using connections.
किसी को भी कनेक्शन के इस्तेमाल के बारे में बात नहीं करनी चाहिए ।
Now we can't even talk about it?
अब तो हम इस बारे में बात भी नहीं कर सकते?
If you had connections, it could've be you.
यदि आपके पास सम्पर्क होते तो यह आप हो सकते थे।
Seriously.
गंभीरता से।
Alright, I know.
ठीक है, मुझे पता है.
Secretary Gu.
सचिव गु.
Handle the onboarding formalities
ऑनबोर्डिंग औपचारिकताओं को संभालें
for this new secretary quickly.
इस नये सचिव के लिए शीघ्रता से काम करें।
Then post his onboarding report
फिर उसकी ऑनबोर्डिंग रिपोर्ट पोस्ट करें
on the notice board in our institute.
हमारे संस्थान के नोटिस बोर्ड पर।
Due to heavy workload at the institute,
संस्थान में कार्यभार अधिक होने के कारण,
Director Lee's new secretary will soon assume duty.
निदेशक ली के नए सचिव जल्द ही कार्यभार संभालेंगे।
[Director Lee's new secretary will soon join] Personnel changes are never announced.
[निदेशक ली के नए सचिव जल्द ही शामिल होंगे] कार्मिक परिवर्तन की कभी घोषणा नहीं की जाती है।
Times have changed.
समय बदल गया है.
Not only will I announce it,
मैं न केवल इसकी घोषणा करूंगा,
I'll make it in big red letters.
मैं इसे बड़े लाल अक्षरों में लिखूंगा।
I must let everyone in our institute
मुझे हमारे संस्थान में सभी को यह बताना होगा कि
see it.
इसे देखें।
What are you trying to do?
आप क्या करने का प्रयास कर रहे हैं?
He broke one of my legs.
उसने मेरा एक पैर तोड़ दिया.
I'll break one of his arms.
मैं उसका एक हाथ तोड़ दूँगा.
[Director Lee's new secretary will soon join]
[निदेशक ली के नए सचिव जल्द ही शामिल होंगे]
Last month, negotiations among the Foreign Ministry,
पिछले महीने विदेश मंत्रालय और विदेश मंत्री के बीच बातचीत हुई थी।
the UK and US went very poorly.
ब्रिटेन और अमेरिका में स्थिति बहुत खराब रही।
So the Japanese have already brought in specialists
इसलिए जापानियों ने पहले ही विशेषज्ञ बुला लिए हैं।
to investigate pro-British and pro-American forces
ब्रिटिश समर्थक और अमेरिकी समर्थक ताकतों की जांच करने के लिए
within the intelligence agencies.
खुफिया एजेंसियों के भीतर।
As for Joseph Lee,
जहाँ तक जोसेफ ली का प्रश्न है,
his ties with Britain and America are too deep.
ब्रिटेन और अमेरिका के साथ उसके संबंध बहुत गहरे हैं।
So once war breaks out,
अतः एक बार युद्ध छिड़ जाए,
he will definitely be cast aside.
उसे निश्चित रूप से दरकिनार कर दिया जाएगा।
Ding Yi is just an informant.
डिंग यी सिर्फ एक मुखबिर है।
His role is to provide you cover.
उसकी भूमिका आपको सुरक्षा प्रदान करना है।
Once that cover fails,
एक बार वह आवरण विफल हो जाए,
casting him aside is inevitable.
उसे एक तरफ कर देना अपरिहार्य है।
As long as you remain in the institute,
जब तक आप संस्थान में रहेंगे,
the Sword Thrust Operation goes on.
तलवार वार अभियान जारी है।
I'm already planning
मैं पहले से ही योजना बना रहा हूँ
to use the Japanese purge of British and American forces
ब्रिटिश और अमेरिकी सेनाओं के जापानी सफाए का उपयोग करने के लिए
as a pretext
एक बहाने के रूप में
to formally report Joseph Lee by name for having overly close ties
जोसेफ ली के अत्यधिक घनिष्ठ संबंध होने के कारण औपचारिक रूप से उनके नाम की रिपोर्ट करना
with British and American personnel.
ब्रिटिश और अमेरिकी कर्मियों के साथ।
This way,
इस तरह,
Ding Yi will be completely out of the game.
डिंग यी पूरी तरह से खेल से बाहर हो जाएगा ।
And I
और मैं
will remain to continue my mission.
मैं अपना मिशन जारी रखूंगा।
Hasn't Liang Jingyuan always been trying to win you over?
क्या लियांग जिंगयुआन हमेशा से आपको जीतने की कोशिश नहीं करता रहा है?
He hates Joseph Lee to the core.
वह जोसेफ ली से बेहद नफरत करता है।
You might as well sign
आप भी हस्ताक्षर कर सकते हैं
the letter of accusation he gave you
आरोप पत्र जो उसने आपको दिया था
and let him be the one to hand it in.
और उसे ही इसे सौंपने दो।
I will use Liang Jingyuan to do it,
मैं इसे करने के लिए लियांग जिंगयुआन का उपयोग करूंगा,
but I will personally write this letter.
लेकिन मैं यह पत्र व्यक्तिगत रूप से लिखूंगा।
[Joseph Lee]
[जोसेफ ली]
I understand what you mean.
मुझे आपकी बात का अर्थ समझ में आ गया।
You just want
आप बस चाहते हैं
to control the wording of this letter
इस पत्र के शब्दों को नियंत्रित करने के लिए
so Ding Yi can leave alive.
ताकि डिंग यी जीवित बच सके।
But you know what Liang Jingyuan is like.
लेकिन आप जानते हैं कि लिआंग जिंगयुआन कैसा है।
Do you think he won't figure it out?
क्या आपको लगता है कि वह इसका पता नहीं लगा पाएगा?
If preserving Ding Yi
यदि डिंग यी को संरक्षित किया जाए
causes Liang Jingyuan to lose trust in you...
लिआंग जिंगयुआन का आप पर से भरोसा उठ गया...
Gu Yangshan,
गु यांगशान,
I advise you to put the bigger picture first,
मैं आपको सलाह देता हूं कि आप पहले बड़ी तस्वीर देखें ,
and not act on emotion.
और भावना पर आधारित कार्य न करें।
[Accused by Charlie Gu]
[चार्ली गु द्वारा आरोपित]
Luo Han, I understand what you mean.
लुओ हान, मैं समझता हूं कि आपका क्या मतलब है।
But you should know
लेकिन आपको पता होना चाहिए
that Ding Yi knows our identities inside out.
कि डिंग यी हमारी पहचान को अंदर से बाहर तक जानता है।
So if we push him too hard,
इसलिए यदि हम उस पर बहुत अधिक दबाव डालेंगे,
it will inevitably affect our subsequent actions.
यह अनिवार्य रूप से हमारे आगामी कार्यों को प्रभावित करेगा ।
So I have my own plans.
इसलिए मेरी अपनी योजनाएँ हैं।
You just need to follow my instructions
आपको बस मेरे निर्देशों का पालन करना होगा
and report to higher-ups, and that's all.
और उच्च अधिकारियों को रिपोर्ट करें, बस इतना ही।
Director Lee.
निर्देशक ली.
Are you going home?
क्या आप घर जा रहे हैं?
Secretary Gu.
सचिव गु.
No, no, it's Commissioner Gu now.
नहीं, नहीं, अब यह कमिश्नर गु है।
Congratulations on your promotion.
तुम्हारी तरक्की के लिए बधाई।
Director Lee, no wonder you wanted to hire a new secretary.
निदेशक ली, इसमें कोई आश्चर्य नहीं कि आप एक नया सचिव नियुक्त करना चाहते थे।
So Commissioner Gu has been promoted to the Pacification Committee.
इसलिए कमिश्नर गु को शांति समिति में पदोन्नत किया गया है ।
Commissioner Gu, congratulations.
कमिश्नर गु, बधाई।
Yes, yes.
हां हां।
Congratulations.
बधाई हो।
Director Lee is truly capable.
निर्देशक ली सचमुच सक्षम हैं।
Even his secretary got a promotion.
यहां तक ​​कि उनके सचिव को भी पदोन्नति मिल गई।
Yes, yes, congratulations.
हाँ, हाँ, बधाई हो।
We're leaving now. See you tomorrow.
हम अब जा रहे हैं। कल मिलते हैं।
See you tomorrow.
कल मिलते हैं।
[Letter of Appointment]
[नियुक्ति पत्र]
[Charlie Gu]
[चार्ली गु]
Congratulations,
बधाई हो,
Commissioner Gu.
आयुक्त गु.
You actually got transferred to work in the Pacification Committee.
आपको वास्तव में शांति समिति में काम करने के लिए स्थानांतरित कर दिया गया है।
Congratulations to you too,
आपको भी मुबारक हो,
on successfully bringing in a new secretary
नए सचिव को सफलतापूर्वक लाने पर
to replace my work.
मेरे काम को बदलने के लिए.
It seems I really underestimated Liang Jingyuan.
ऐसा लगता है कि मैंने सचमुच लिआंग जिंगयुआन को कम आंका था।
I thought he just held an empty title,
मैंने सोचा कि उसके पास बस एक खाली शीर्षक है,
but I didn't expect
लेकिन मुझे उम्मीद नहीं थी
he actually has some real power.
वास्तव में उसके पास कुछ वास्तविक शक्ति है।
But what I'm really curious about is
लेकिन मैं वास्तव में जिस बात को लेकर उत्सुक हूं वह यह है
he used his wife to trade for his future.
उसने अपने भविष्य के लिए अपनी पत्नी का इस्तेमाल किया।
But what about you?
लेकिन आपका क्या?
What did you use?
आपने क्या उपयोग किया?
The new secretary Xian Biyun got for you
नया सचिव जियान बियुन आपके लिए लाया है
should assume his duty tomorrow.
उन्हें कल अपना कार्यभार संभालना चाहिए।
I'll complete the handover as soon as possible.
मैं यथाशीघ्र हैंडओवर पूरा कर दूंगा ।
From now on,
अब से,
we'll each go our own way and not interfere with each other.
हम सभी अपने-अपने रास्ते चलेंगे और एक-दूसरे के काम में हस्तक्षेप नहीं करेंगे।
Wanting to replace the Pacification Committee's code?
क्या आप शांति समिति के कोड को बदलना चाहते हैं ?
I won't let you succeed.
मैं तुम्हें सफल नहीं होने दूँगा.
Mr. Lee, please come with us.
श्री ली, कृपया हमारे साथ आइए।
[Pacification Committee, Shanghai Branch]
[शांति समिति, शंघाई शाखा]
Commissioner Gu.
आयुक्त गु.
This way.
इस तरह.
Mr. Hashimoto, this is Charlie Gu.
श्री हाशिमोटो, मैं चार्ली गु हूं।
I'll go to the conference room.
मैं सम्मेलन कक्ष में जाऊँगा।
Yes.
हाँ।
Mr. Hashimoto Taro,
श्री हाशिमोतो तारो,
head of the Code Development Team.
कोड विकास टीम के प्रमुख.
The code for our committee's secret radio
हमारी समिति के गुप्त रेडियो का कोड
was designed by him.
उनके द्वारा डिजाइन किया गया था।
His design?
उसका डिज़ाइन?
Yes.
हाँ।
But as far as I know,
लेकिन जहाँ तक मुझे पता है,
isn't Nanjing using
क्या नानजिंग इसका उपयोग नहीं कर रहा है?
Mr. Joseph Lee's code?
श्री जोसेफ ली का कोड?
I don't know
मुझें नहीं पता
the specific reasons for that.
इसके विशिष्ट कारण.
However, we've always used
हालाँकि, हमने हमेशा इसका उपयोग किया है
Mr. Hashimoto's code.
श्री हाशिमोटो का कोड.
Your workstation is here.
आपका कार्यस्थान यहाँ है.
The head of your decryption team
आपकी डिक्रिप्शन टीम का प्रमुख
hasn't arrived yet.
अभी तक नहीं आया है.
I'll introduce him to you when he gets here.
जब वह यहां आएगा तो मैं उसका आपसे परिचय कराऊंगा ।
Decryption team?
डिक्रिप्शन टीम?
Yes.
हाँ।
Commissioner Gu,
आयुक्त गु,
didn't you say earlier
क्या तुमने पहले नहीं कहा था?
you had something to give Major General Sasaki?
क्या आपके पास मेजर जनरल सासाकी को देने के लिए कुछ था?
No rush.
कोई जल्दी नहीं।
Just some routine work plans.
बस कुछ नियमित कार्य योजनाएँ।
Has Mr. Liang arrived?
क्या श्री लियांग आ गए हैं?
Mr. Liang probably hasn't arrived yet.
श्री लियांग शायद अभी तक नहीं पहुंचे हैं।
Why are you looking for him?
तुम उसे क्यों ढूंढ रहे हो?
Nothing. Please, carry on.
कुछ नहीं। कृपया, आगे बढ़ें।
Okay.
ठीक है।
Please go ahead.
कृपया आगे जाएं।
Charlie.
चार्ली.
Mr. Liang.
श्री लियांग.
Just call me Liang.
बस मुझे लिआंग कहो.
I was just about to look for you.
मैं तो बस तुम्हें ढूँढने ही वाला था।
There are some things I don't understand.
कुछ बातें ऐसी हैं जो मुझे समझ नहीं आतीं।
I'd like you to explain them to me.
मैं चाहता हूं कि आप मुझे इनके बारे में समझाएं।
Say it.
यह कहना।
Why does the Pacification Committee
शांति समिति क्यों
use Hashimoto's code?
हाशिमोटो के कोड का उपयोग करें?
And why have I been assigned to the decryption team?
और मुझे डिक्रिप्शन टीम में क्यों नियुक्त किया गया है ?
Your promises
आपके वादे
continue to be disappointing.
निराशाजनक बने हुए हैं।
Listen to me...
मेरी बात सुनो...
Sasaki has already handed over the letter of accusation you wrote
सासाकी ने आपके द्वारा लिखा गया आरोप पत्र पहले ही सौंप दिया है
to Lieutenant General Yasui.
लेफ्टिनेंट जनरल यासुई को।
He was furious after reading it.
इसे पढ़कर वह क्रोधित हो गया।
I'm telling you,
मैं तुम्हें बता रहा हूँ,
Joseph Lee will definitely be dead this time.
इस बार जोसेफ ली निश्चित रूप से मर जाएगा।
As long as he's finished this time,
जब तक वह इस बार काम पूरा कर लेगा,
you'll become the director of the Cryptography Institute.
आप क्रिप्टोग्राफी संस्थान के निदेशक बन जायेंगे ।
Why care about a mere Code Officer position?
मात्र कोड अधिकारी पद की परवाह क्यों करें ?
What are you saying?
आप क्या कह रहे हैं?
I know what you're thinking.
मैं जानता हूं तुम क्या सोच्र रहे हो।
Your letter of accusation
आपका आरोप पत्र
didn't really prove that Joseph Lee
वास्तव में यह साबित नहीं हुआ कि जोसेफ ली
secretly had ties to Britain and America.
गुप्त रूप से ब्रिटेन और अमेरिका से संबंध थे ।
But it's not important.
लेकिन यह महत्वपूर्ण नहीं है.
What's important is that this letter of accusation
महत्वपूर्ण बात यह है कि आरोप पत्र
serves as Joseph Lee's death warrant.
यह जोसेफ ली की मौत का वारंट है।
Mr. Lee,
श्री ली,
every word spoken here
यहाँ बोला गया हर शब्द
will be recorded.
दर्ज किया जाएगा.
If found to be false, it is a serious crime.
यदि यह झूठा पाया गया तो यह एक गंभीर अपराध है।
According to Japanese wartime law, it's punishable by death.
जापानी युद्धकालीन कानून के अनुसार, इसके लिए मृत्युदंड का प्रावधान है।
What do you mean?
आपका क्या मतलब है?
Do you think Sasaki
क्या आपको लगता है कि सासाकी
went through all this trouble
इन सारी परेशानियों से गुज़रा
just to get rid of a blind man
बस एक अंधे आदमी से छुटकारा पाने के लिए
who doesn't have much time left?
किसके पास ज्यादा समय नहीं बचा है?
Of course not.
बिल्कुल नहीं।
We received a report
हमें एक रिपोर्ट प्राप्त हुई
that you were intentionally monopolizing
कि आप जानबूझकर एकाधिकार कर रहे थे
code design work in the New Government.
नई सरकार में कोड डिजाइन का काम।
Was this authorized by the Tonoji family?
क्या यह टोनोजी परिवार द्वारा अधिकृत था?
He wants to use Joseph Lee
वह जोसेफ ली का उपयोग करना चाहता है
to falsely accuse
झूठा आरोप लगाना
the Tonoji family of colluding with the enemy.
टोनोजी परिवार पर दुश्मन के साथ मिलीभगत का आरोप लगाया गया।
That's nonsense.
यह बकवास है.
This is completely unfounded.
यह पूरी तरह से निराधार है।
I know nothing about it.
मैं इसके बारे में कुछ नहीं जानता।
Once this is done,
एक बार यह हो जाए,
there will be no one left
कोई नहीं बचेगा
to stand up to Tōjō Hideki.
तोजो हिदेकी के सामने खड़े होने के लिए।
Your father was the mathematics tutor
आपके पिता गणित के शिक्षक थे
for the Grand Duke Tonoji
ग्रैंड ड्यूक टोनोजी के लिए
and often visited the Tonoji residence.
और अक्सर टोनोजी निवास पर जाते थे।
At Grand Duke's residence,
ग्रैंड ड्यूक के निवास पर,
which British personnel did you meet?
आप किस ब्रिटिश कर्मचारी से मिले?
Grand Duke was personally appointed by His Majesty the Emperor
ग्रैंड ड्यूक को महामहिम सम्राट द्वारा व्यक्तिगत रूप से नियुक्त किया गया था
as ambassador to the UK.
ब्रिटेन में राजदूत के रूप में।
He has always been loyal to the Emperor.
वह हमेशा सम्राट के प्रति वफादार रहा है।
He has never had any contact
उनका कभी कोई संपर्क नहीं हुआ
with British personnel outside of work,
काम के बाहर ब्रिटिश कर्मियों के साथ,
let alone secretly inviting them
उन्हें गुप्त रूप से आमंत्रित करना तो दूर की बात है
to his house.
अपने घर के लिए।
Lieutenant General Yasui,
लेफ्टिनेंट जनरल यासुई,
you can doubt me,
आप मुझ पर शक कर सकते हैं,
but you absolutely should not doubt Grand Duke.
लेकिन आपको ग्रैंड ड्यूक पर बिल्कुल भी संदेह नहीं करना चाहिए।
Charlie, you should consider yourself lucky.
चार्ली, तुम्हें अपने आप को भाग्यशाली समझना चाहिए।
You've offered this blade,
आपने यह ब्लेड पेश किया है,
proving your loyalty.
अपनी वफ़ादारी साबित करना.
You have to think long term.
आपको दीर्घकालिक सोचना होगा।
So I want to
तो मैं चाहता हूँ
thank you for this promotion,
इस पदोन्नति के लिए धन्यवाद,
for pulling me out of
मुझे बाहर निकालने के लिए
this political whirlpool?
इस राजनीतिक भंवर में?
Don't forget, we're friends.
मत भूलो, हम दोस्त हैं।
Why say such things?
ऐसी बातें क्यों कहते हो?
Sasaki and I both admire you.
सासाकी और मैं दोनों आपकी प्रशंसा करते हैं।
Talent like you is hard to come by.
आप जैसी प्रतिभा पाना कठिन है।
Don't let everyone down.
हर किसी को निराश मत करो.
Mr. Lee,
श्री ली,
before this matter is fully investigated,
इससे पहले कि इस मामले की पूरी तरह से जांच हो,
starting from today,
आज से शुरू,
all your Cryptography Institute duties will be suspended.
आपके सभी क्रिप्टोग्राफी संस्थान कर्तव्य निलंबित कर दिए जाएंगे।
Wait for our inquiry at any time
किसी भी समय हमारी पूछताछ की प्रतीक्षा करें
until the investigation is completed.
जब तक जांच पूरी नहीं हो जाती।
♪Flames dancing alone♪
♪अकेले नाचती लपटें♪
♪Broken candle wax♪
♪टूटी हुई मोमबत्ती का मोम♪
♪Holding onto the warmth♪
♪गर्मी को थामे रखना♪
♪Eyes tinted red with light♪
♪आँखें रोशनी से लाल हो गईं♪
♪Flickering dimness♪
♪ टिमटिमाती धुंधलका ♪
♪A lonely little lamp♪
♪एक अकेला छोटा सा दीपक♪
♪Flowers cradle morning dew♪
♪फूल सुबह की ओस को झुलाते हैं♪
♪Cracked skin♪
♪ फटी त्वचा ♪
♪Turns back into earth♪
♪वापस धरती में बदल जाता है♪
♪When the sun rises♪
♪जब सूरज उगता है♪
♪That very first light♪
♪वह पहली रोशनी♪
♪Will dance for me♪
♪मेरे लिए नाचोगे♪
♪Home lost in the mist♪
♪धुंध में खोया घर♪
♪Nowhere to go♪
♪कहीं नहीं जाना है♪
♪And nowhere to retreat♪
♪और पीछे हटने के लिए कहीं नहीं♪
♪I swallowed the pain again♪
♪मैंने फिर से दर्द निगल लिया♪
♪A real life or a play?♪
♪वास्तविक जीवन या नाटक?♪
♪It's hard to tell♪
♪यह बताना मुश्किल है♪
♪Where does the wind go?♪
♪हवा कहाँ जाती है?♪
♪Whose window does it shake?♪
♪यह किसकी खिड़की हिलाता है?♪
♪It whispers softly♪
♪यह धीरे से फुसफुसाता है♪
♪It rustles in my heart♪
♪यह मेरे दिल में सरसराहट करता है♪
♪Maybe you or maybe me♪
♪शायद आप या शायद मैं♪
♪Caught in the sorrow♪
♪दुःख में फँसा हुआ♪
♪Someone keeps the watch♪
♪कोई तो नज़र रखता है♪
♪On the vast plains♪
♪विशाल मैदानों पर♪
♪Tears gently fall♪
♪आँसू धीरे से गिरते हैं♪
♪Cracked wounds linger on♪
♪ टूटे हुए घाव बने रहते हैं ♪
♪Someone keeps the watch♪
♪कोई तो नज़र रखता है♪
♪Wandering in the shadows♪
♪छाया में भटकना♪
♪Nightfall closes in♪
♪रात ढलने वाली है♪
♪When we turn back, dawn appears♪
♪जब हम पीछे मुड़ते हैं, तो भोर दिखाई देती है♪
♪Someone keeps the watch♪
♪कोई तो नज़र रखता है♪
♪On the vast plains♪
♪विशाल मैदानों पर♪
♪Tears gently fall♪
♪आँसू धीरे से गिरते हैं♪
♪Cracked wounds linger on♪
♪ टूटे हुए घाव बने रहते हैं ♪
♪Someone keeps the watch♪
♪कोई तो नज़र रखता है♪
♪Wandering in the shadows♪
♪छाया में भटकना♪
♪Nightfall closes in♪
♪रात ढलने वाली है♪
♪When we turn back, dawn appears♪
♪जब हम पीछे मुड़ते हैं, तो भोर दिखाई देती है♪